Finding Aid to the Dee Mosbacher papers and Woman Vision records SSC.MS.00740
Sophia Smith Collection
Dee Mosbacher papers and Woman Vision records
1950-2015
1980-2013
Sophia Smith Collection
Woman Vision Productions
SSC.MS.00740
63.52 linear feet (104 boxes)
1,617.4 Gigabytes (28,290 digital files and 160 disc images)
Diane (Dee) Mosbacher is an activist, filmmaker, and practicing psychiatrist. Her production company, Woman Vision, has produced films with themes touching on homophobia in various contexts, women's history, and the lived experiences of people who are gay and lesbian. This collection documents Mosbacher's personal life and professional life both through and outside of Woman Vision. It includes writings by and about Mosbacher, paper records from Woman Vision's projects, and a large amount of audiovisual materials from those productions.
Accruals
Additional donations of materials are expected.
Biographical Note
Diane (Dee) Mosbacher, MD, PhD, was born in Houston, Texas on January 13, 1949 to Jane Pennybacker (1926-1970) and businessman Robert Adam Mosbacher, Sr. (1927-2010). She has three siblings, Robert Mosbacher, Jr. (1951-), Kathryn Mosbacher (1953), and Lisa Mosbacher Mears (1956-).
Dee Mosbacher's wife is Nanette Gartrell, M.D., formerly a professor of psychiatry at Harvard Medical School and the University of California, San Francisco, and, since 2009, a Visiting Distinguished Scholar at the Williams Institute, University of California, Los Angeles, School of Law. Gartrell is the principal investigator of the U. S. National Longitudinal Lesbian Family Study (NLLFS), the largest, longest-running prospective investigation of lesbian mothers and their children in the United States. The two have been together since 1975 and married in 2004 (annulled by the State of California) and 2005. Dr. Dee Mosbacher and Dr. Nanette Gartrell live and work in San Francisco.
Dee Mosbacher received her primary and secondary education at Kinkaid School from which she graduated in 1967. She graduated from Pitzer College with a B.A. in psychology in 1972. She received a doctorate in social psychology from Union Graduate School in 1979 and a medical degree from Baylor College of Medicine in 1983. She was a medical intern at Cambridge Hospital through Harvard Medical School from 1983-1984 and was a psychiatry resident in the same hospital from 1984-1987.
Dee Mosbacher became a women's health activist in college and began directing documentary films as a student at Baylor College and as a resident at Harvard Medical School. Her films focused on discrimination against lesbian and gay physicians and patients, and she wrote many articles about gay and lesbian patients for the academic and medical community.
Dee Mosbacher's father, Robert A. Mosbacher, Sr., was a Texas oil and gas producer, who served as a chief fundraiser for five Republican presidential campaigns. Robert, Sr. served as Commerce Secretary under President George H. W. Bush but left his post in 1992 to raise funds for Bush's reelection campaign. The Republican Party intensified their anti-gay, anti-abortion rhetoric during this time period, which was a point of contention for Robert, Sr. and his daughter Dee, who spoke out against the Republican Party's use of homophobia as a fundraising tool in the 1992 election.
In 1992, Dee Mosbacher founded the non-profit production company Woman Vision to counteract the media campaign on LGBT issues conducted by the Republican Party, which was the focus of the 1992 Republican National Convention. As a psychiatrist, Mosbacher understood the psychological and psychosocial suffering caused by homophobia and created Woman Vision to promote equal treatment of all people through the production and use of educational media. Woman Vision promotes positive role models and supportive images of societally marginalized people. It uses diversity trainings, lectures, and other educational outreach programs to encourage people to abandon their homophobia and to improve the lives of LGBT individuals. Dr. Mosbacher has directed and produced nine documentaries, which have received a total of forty-six awards nationally and internationally, including a 1994 Academy Award nomination for Best Documentary Short Film for Straight From the Heart. This film was screened at a bipartisan event for Congress in 1995.
Dee Mosbacher has been a recipient of numerous awards, including the 1992 National Gay and Lesbian Task Force Creating Change Award for "courage and honesty in challenging the Republican Party's tactics;" the 1993 NOW Women of Power Award; the 1997 Lambda Liberty Award; the 2002 Pitzer College award "for unwavering support of our goal of educating students to social responsibility and for being a model in her own life of that goal;" the 2009 Barbara Gittings Award; the 2014 John E. Fryer Award from the American Psychiatric Association for "contributing to the mental health of sexual minorities;" and, as a co-recipient with Dr. Nanette Gartrell, the 2014 Legal Aid Society Mathew O. Tobriner Public Service Award.
In 1991, Dee Mosbacher was the first Pitzer College graduate to deliver a commencement address at her alma mater. In 2010, she established the Mosbacher/Gartrell Center for Media Experimentation and Activism at Pitzer College.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use with following restrictions on access: box 104 is temporarily restricted while a determination about the sensitivity of the content is made. This box contains materials from nearly every sub-series in the collection which were separated during processing because they contain third-party contact information.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following collections at Smith College Special Collections:
Nanette K. Gartrell papers
Joan E. Biren papers
Boden Sandstrom papers
Eleanor Sanger papers
Diana Davies papers
Women's Music Archives Records
Sports Collection
Music Collection
Documenting Lesbian Lives Oral History Project
Scope and Contents
The Dee Mosbacher papers and Woman Vision records document Dee Mosbacher's personal and professional life, both within and beyond her film production company, Woman Vision.
The first series of Mosbacher's personal and professional papers includes a small amount of material from her days as a graduate and medical student, and a small amount of digitized and bon digital photographs and other personal historical materials, but mostly documents her life and work in the 1980s and 1990s. It includes articles about her, as well as materials she authored, speeches she gave, and two films she produced that were directed by Joan E. Biren (JEB).
The bulk of the collection is in the second series, which documents the work of the non-profit film production company Dee Mosbacher founded in 1992, Woman Vision. This series includes paper files about the funding, production, publicity, and response to the films, as well as a significant amount of audiovisual materials such as raw footage of interviews and other materials used in the films, early edits of the films, digital video production files, and final cuts.
The films that Woman Vision has produced cover a range of topics, but notable themes include issues around homophobia in various social, racial, and religious contexts; homophobia in medicine and sports; women's history; and the lived experiences of gay and lesbian people, particularly those of color.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Dee Mosbacher in two transfers, one in 2014 and one in 2015.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials and computer media in this collection. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request the creation of and access to digital copies.
This collection contains materials received from the donor in digital form that are not currently available online; please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content. Note that Special Collections may not be able to provide required software for some file formats.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in two series based on type of content. Series 1. Dee Mosbacher personal and professional papers includes personal materials and professional materials produced outside of Woman Vision, while Series 2. Woman Vision documents the company's productions.
Other Finding Aids
Item-level inventories of audiovisual materials and electronic records are available, but not yet integrated into this finding aid. Please contact specialcollections@smith.edu to request copies of these lists.
AIDS (Disease) -- United States; African American families -- Religious life; Latino -- Family life; Homophobia in sports -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Women athletes -- History -- Sources; Women's music; Women's music -- Performances; Women's music -- History -- Sources; Lesbian activists -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Lesbian athletes -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Lesbian musicians -- History -- United States; Lesbian physicians; Lesbianism -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Lesbians -- Songs and music; Lesbians in motion pictures; Homosexuality -- Psychological aspects -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Homosexuality -- Religious aspects -- Christianity; Business records; Digital files; Electronic records; Interviews; Motion pictures; photographs; Sound recordings; Videotapes; Martin, Del (Dorothy "Del" Louise Taliaferro Martin), 1921-2008; Lyon, Phyllis (Phyllis Ann Lyon), 1924; Gartrell, Nanette Kathryn; Mosbacher, Dee; Biren, Joan E.; Sandstrom, Boden C.; Adam, Margie; Mosbacher, Dee; Mosbacher, Dee
- Dee Mosbacher personal and professional papers, 1977-2015; 1; 2.24 linear feet (6 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The Dee Mosbacher personal and professional papers series contains biographical information about Dee Mosbacher, as well as documentation of her personal life and professional work outside of Woman Vision.
  The earliest materials in this series date from her time as a graduate student in the 1970s, and include an "Original Lammas" T-shirt, a play written under the name "Li Garland," 1977 letters of recommendation following a 1-month clerkship through Harvard Medical School, and a copy of her doctoral dissertation.
  Later materials in the series documenting Dee Mosbacher's career include a 2014 copy of her curriculum vitae and copies of her speeches, presentations, and writings, including a recording of her 1991 commencement speech at Pitzer. The series contains two folders of documents related to the U.S. National Longitudinal Lesbian Family Study.
  Of particular note in this series are copies of audiovisual presentations aimed at medical students that were directed by Joan E. Biren (JEB) and produced by Dee Mosbacher prior to the founding of Woman Vision: Closets are Health Hazards: Gay and Lesbian Physicians Come Out (1985) and Lesbian Physicians on Practice, Patients and Power (1991).
  The series also includes numerous writings about Dee Mosbacher, information about awards she received, the text of a "Toast to Dee" at her sixtieth birthday written by her wife Nanette Gartrell, as well as a small number of photographic prints from the early 2000s and digital photographs and files from throughout her life.
  - Articles about Dee Mosbacher, approximately 1988-2014; 17 folders (Box 1, Folder 1-17)
  - Awards, 1987-1995 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Conferences and Presentations, 1986-2014 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1991-2009 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Original Lammas T-shirt, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letters of recommendation based on Harvard Medical School, Massachusetts Mental Health Center clinical clerkship, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 2005-2007 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Seattle Gay News, 1992-1993; 2 folders (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Speeches, approximately 1992-2014; 2 folders (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - "Ceremonies on Foot" by Minnie Bruce, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Toast to Dee On the Occasion of her Sixtieth Birthday Celebration" by Nanette Gartrell, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Writings by Mosbacher: Say Hello Before You Leave, Play by Li Garland, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Writings by Mosbacher: Dissertation, "Self and Self Help for the Schizophrenic Patient", 1979; 2 folders (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Writings by Mosbacher: A Tale of Two Hospitals: A Comparison of Treatment Programs for Schizophrenia, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Writings by Mosbacher: The Price, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Writings by Mosbacher: Lesbian Alcohol and Substance Abuse, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Writings by Mosbacher: Case III: Lesbian Couple Considering Children, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Writings by Mosbacher: Medical Muddle, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Writings by Mosbacher: Alcohol and Other Drug Use in Female Medical Students: A Comparison of Lesbians and Heterosexuals, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Writings by Mosbacher: Effectiveness of Vitamin E for Treatment of Long-Term Tardive Dyskinesia, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Writings by Mosbacher: Screening for psychosocial problems in 4-5 year olds during routine EPSDT examinations..., 1995 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Writings by Mosbacher: Haloperidol Dose and Blood Level Variability..., 1995 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Writings by Mosbacher: The Roles to Recovery, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Recording of commencement speech by Mosbacher at Pitzer College, 1991 (Box 3)
    Videotapes
  - "Dee 2014 Fryer Award Film Retrospective" digital files, 4.5 Gigabytes (2 digital files copied from flash drive) (Box 3)
    Video recording made for this event, as well as still images and film clips used in the video.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    This digital content is not currently available online; please consult with Special Collections staff to request access.
  - Personal digital photos and files, 1949-2014; 10.5 Gigabytes (1,583 digital files copied from 1 flash drive) (Box 3)
    Digital backup of Dee Mosbacher's personal computer files, 1949-2014. File types include jpg, tif, docx, and pdf. See digital file list for filenames. Printed file list in box.
    Electronic records
  - Closets are Health Hazards: Gay and Lesbian Physicians Come Out, 1980-1988; 2 boxes (Box 4, Box 5)
    Closets are Health Hazards: Gay and Lesbian Physicians Come Out (1985) is a slide tape and video presentation used in medical school human sexuality courses and conferences in the U.S. and Europe. Produced by Dee Mosbacher and directed by Joan E. Biren (JEB). This file is comprised of audiovisual materials and slides.
    Slides; Audiotapes
  - Lesbian Physicians on Practice, Patients, and Power, 1991-1993 (Box 6)
    Lesbian Physicians on Practice, Patients, and Power (1991) is a 30-minute video sent by the American Association of Physicians for Human Rights to every medical school in the U.S. and Canada. Produced by Dee Mosbacher, and directed by Joan E. Biren (JEB). This file is comprised of audiovisual materials and a flyer.
- Woman Vision records, 1950-2014; 1984-2013; 2; 61.28 linear feet (97 boxes)
  The Woman Vision series contains manuscript and audiovisual material related to Mosbacher's production company, Woman Vision. This series includes records related to the following Woman Vision productions:
  Straight from the Heart (1994) an Academy Award-nominated film about parents of lesbian and gay children
  Out for a Change: Addressing Homophobia in Women's Sports (1994)
  All God's Children (1996), which presents an analysis of sexual orientation within a context of traditional African American values
  De Colores (2001), a bilingual documentary about Latino families unlearning homophobia
  Radical Harmonies (2002), about the women's music movement
  No Secret Anymore: The Times of Del Martin and Phyllis Lyon (2003)
  Training Rules (2008) about women's collegiate athletics
  The Last Challenge (2012-2014), a web campaign against homophobia in men's sports
  Although the specific records vary by project, generally they include information both about the film's creation, as well as its publicity, reception and awards. The series often includes production files, funding information, research files, correspondence, interview transcripts, photographs, and raw footage, working edits, digital video production files, and final prints of the films.
  Arrangement
  The materials in the Woman Vision records series are organized in chronological order by project release date.
  - Straight from the Heart, 1984-2014
    Straight from the Heart (1994) is a 24-minute Academy Award-nominated film that explores parents' journeys to a new understanding of their adult lesbian and gay children. Co-produced/co-directed with Dee Mosbacher and Frances Reid. This subseries is comprised of correspondence, photographs, articles, transcripts, research, and audiovisual materials.
    - Academy Awards, 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Administrative, 1993-1994 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Articles, 1994-2014 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Congressional screening of Straight from the Heart, 1995-1996 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Production Photographs, 1994-1995; 2 folders (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
    - Project Heart, 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Research, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - The Gay Truth transcripts, undated, 13 folders (Box 7, Folder 10-18, Box 8, Folder 1-4)
    - The Gay Truth transcripts, family interview audiovisual materials, 1993-1995; 5.5 boxes (Box 9, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12, Box 13, Box 14)
    - Audiovisual materials, 1994-1995; 2.5 boxes (Box 14, Box 15, Box 16)
  - Out for a Change: Addressing Homophobia in Women's Sports, 1953-2005; 1991-1995
    Out for a Change: Addressing Homophobia in Women's Sports (1994) is a 28-minute film that exposes the devastating emotional impact that homophobia has on all women athletes, regardless of their sexual orientation. Produced and directed by Dee Mosbacher. This subseries is comprised of administrative and research records, as well as correspondence, photographs, and audiovisual materials.
    - Administrative: Crew and equipment, 1993-1994 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Administrative: Distribution, 1995-1996; 2 folders (Box 17, Folder 2-3)
    - Administrative: General, undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Administrative: Funding, 1979-1994; 2 folders (Box 17, Folder 5-7)
    - Administrative: Homophobia curriculum, undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Administrative: Homophobia in men's sports, 1994-1995 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Administrative: Media distribution: UC Berkeley Extension, 2004 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Administrative: Permissions and releases, 1994-1995 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Administrative: Production notes, 1993-1994 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Administrative: Proposal, 1988-1990 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Administrative: Quotes, 1994 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Administrative: Stock footage, 1994; 2 folders (Box 17, Folder 15-16)
    - John Schlafly article, approximately 1992-1993 (Box 18)
    - Correspondence: general, 1991-1993; 5 folders (Box 18, Folder 2-6)
    - Correspondence: Homophobia and men's sports, 1998 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence: Homophobia and women's sports, 1998 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Interviews, 1968 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Interviews: Edit lists, approximately 1992-1994; 9 folders (Box 18, Folder 10-18)
    - Interviews: Tape logs, approximately 1991-1994 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Notes, 2003 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Photographs, approximately 1991-1994 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Negatives, approximately 1991-1994 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Research: Homophobia and women's sports, 1993 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Research: Homophobia in sports, 1989-1994; 14 folders (Box 19, Folder 6-19)
    - Research: Men's sports (homophobia and sports), 1995-1998; 5 folders (Box 20, Folder 1-5)
    - Research: "Out in the Field" (homophobia and sports), 1998-1999 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Research: Women's sports (homophobia and sports), 1996-1998; 3 folders (Box 20, Folder 7-9)
    - Transcripts: Richmond shoot, approximately 1991-1994; 2 folders (Box 20, Folder 10-11)
    - Oshman's Women and Sports, Grants for Girls Selection Committee, 1995 (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Women's Sports Foundation, 1995-2000 (Box 20, Folder 13-17)
    - Women's Sports Foundation: Homophobia Task Force policy, 1994-1995 (Box 20, Folder 18)
    - Women's Empowerment Project, 1997 (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
    - Women's Empowerment Project research: Fundraising project and additional information, 1996-1998 (Box 21, Folder 3-4)
    - Women's Empowerment Project research: India/Nepal, 1992-1997 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Women's Empowerment Project research: Nicaragua - Puntos de Encuento, approximately 1991-1997 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Women's Empowerment Project research: Nicaragua - WCCN/NCDLF, 1997-1998 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Women's Empowerment Project research: Philanthropy, 1997; 2 folders (Box 21, Folder 8-9)
    - Women's Empowerment Project research: South Africa, 1995 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Women's Empowerment Project research: United States, 1996 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Out for a Change audiovisual materials, 1994-1996 (Box 22)
    - Homophobia and men's and women's sports audiovisual materials, 1953-2005; 4 boxes (Box 23, Box 24, Box 25, Box 26)
      These boxes contain audiovisual material with footage related to primarily homophobia in women's sports, however, there is some material related to homophobia in mens sports. Also included are interviews and footage of women playing sports, such as golf, tennis, and basketball.
  - All God's Children, 1992-2007
    All God's Children (1996) is a 26-minute film that addresses lesbians, gays, and spirituality in the African-American church-going community. Co-produced/co-directed with Frances Reid and Sylvia Rhue. This file is comprised of administrative and research records, as well as audiovisual materials.
    - Administrative: Accounts payable (bills to pay), 1994-1995 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Administrative: Festivals and presentations, 1994-1995 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Administrative: Footage logs, 1995 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Administrative: Interviews, 1995-1998; 2 folders (Box 27, Folder 4-5)
    - Administrative: Materials, approximately 1992-1997 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Administrative: Notes, Approximately 1992-1997 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Administrative: Possible future contacts, 1995 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Administrative: Quotes and promotional material, 1996 (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Administrative: Screenings, 1996-1997 (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Travel, 1995 (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Articles, 1996-1998 (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Photographs: General, approximately 1992-1996 (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Photographs: Production photographs, 1996-1998 (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Negatives: General, approximately 1992-1996 (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Negatives: Production negatives, approximately 1992-1996 (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Research: Bishop Tutu, 1995 (Box 27, Folder 19)
    - Research: General, 1994-1995; 7 folders (Box 27, Folder 20-21, Box 28, Folder 1-5)
    - Film Transcript, approximately 1996 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Tape log and music PPWK, 2007; 14 folders (Box 29, Folder 1-14)
    - All God's Children transcripts, approximately 1996; 13 folders (Box 30, Folder 1-13)
    - Tape logs and audiovisual materials, 1992-1996; 8 boxes (Box 31, Box 32, Box 33, Box 34, Box 35, Box 36, Box 37, Box 38)
      - Computer files for production of All God's Children, 1992-1997; .0033 Gigabytes (6 E01 disk images from 6 floppy disks)